here you can see that if we use this
setup it's literally twice as fast and
we can also use a database that we're
already familiar with to manage our
vectors as well as our documents I think
for most of you out there building
applications with large language models
using PG factor is actually better than
using a dedicated Vector database like
pine cone or wv8 and now I've been
working with large language models for
about a year now and I think this image
is a good overview of what a typical
architecture looks like from a high
level If You're Building an app like
this and if you've dabbled with these
models with retrieval augmented
generation then this should be familiar
and now from the start about one year
ago I started to use pine cone as my
primary factor database because this was
also A New Concept for me so I've never
heard of factor databases never worked
with them and pinec con was put forward
as the factor database for AI
applications so I started to work with
that buil all my applications for my
clients around pine cone and now really
what I've noticed over the past couple
of weeks as some of the applications
that we're building are transitioning
from proof of concept to production
where managing the data that is active
in the factor database becomes more and
more important I've really ran into some
issues where I had to reconsider my data
pipelines and also my Factor databases
and that pointed me to this article as I
was doing some research on finding
alternative ways of working with these
factors and here uh I saw other people
running into some issues as well and
switching to PG factor which got me
interested because PG factor is
essentially a an extension for a post
SQL database to use factors in it and
also perform similarity search and now
I'm already familiar with postur SQL
databases actually I use data grip and
have most of my projects for my clients
where we need a database I have them
available in here in either a postgress
datab base or or something similar so
that immediately caught my attention and
then I thought okay well then but what's
the tradeoff if pine cone is really a
dedicated Factor database then it will
probably be a lot faster right and
that's when I found this really
interesting comparison done by superbase
here it outlined that PG factor is
faster than pine cone so then I thought
hey really what's the point of using a
dedicated Factor database in a separate
environment separate from all of my
other projects um versus just using a
database that I'm already familiar with
and since Lang chain also has a PG
Factor class which works very well I
decided to start experimenting with this
and see what the pros and cons are so I
have a document over here or a script I
should say which I will share with you
as well where I run various experiments
and I will share with you my insights
show you first how to work with the pine
cone index and then what that looks like
if we do the same thing with PG factor
and then I'll show you why I completely
switch to PG Factor right now for all of
my generative AI projects and now to be
clear I'm definitely not an expert on
this so it could very well be that I
just don't have enough information or
knowledge about how to effectively work
with pine cone but I'm just going to
show you some basic examples that I
think will be very relatable to you and
just from a speed and simplicity
perspective PG factor is the clear
winner for me all right so let's walk
you through some examples I'm going to
load up an interactive python session
over here and then we're going to load
some data so I have an ebook over here
the Christmas Carol and let's load that
up so we're going to split all the
documents and here you can see we have
now taken this C or txt file which is in
here it's a huge ebook and we have split
it up into the documents now we're going
to connect with my pine cone account
through the API key in the environment
and then I'm going to run this which
essentially says hey if there's a demo
index uh you can load it if not we'll
create one one I already have the demo
index over here and we can now have a
look at that see what's going on so if
we now come to the pine cone data
Explorer we can see all of the factors
here and the source and then also the
text of the various chunks that have
been put into it okay so this is all
basic pine cone stuff now let's create a
function that we can call to run a query
to do to perform a similarity search and
I'll also create a function that
calculates the time it takes to run the
function and we can also specify a
number of times that we want to run this
function and take the average of the
time so let's see how long it takes if
we search this pine cone index with uh
we have the query over here and it's
just the um it's the first line of the
ebook and now we can see okay we can run
a similarity search and we correctly get
the first chunk of the book back based
on the uh first line line over here from
from the book that we put in and then we
can see that it took
0.53 seconds all right so that was the
pine cone setup I'm going a little fast
but this is just to show you how we set
up this experiment now let's come over
to the pg Vector part and if you want to
follow this yourself you can check out
the repository that I will link in the
description now let's take a collection
name over here and also a connection
string to connect to our database and
now we're going to to create uh the
store similar to how we just creating
the pine cone Factor store now we're
going to use the Lang chain PG Factor
one and just by loading this and putting
in the uh connection to our database I
can now come over here and let's have a
look at what we actually created and
this is one thing that I really like
first and foremost about working with PG
Factor we now um have two tables and
Lang chain creates these automatically
for you if you just put in the
connection to your post SQL database so
we have a collection name which is the
name that we just put in here and then
we also have a embedding table where you
first of all have the collection ID
which maps to The UU ID that you see
over here then we have the embedding and
we also have the original document in
here so we have a traditional structured
SQL data datase but it also has the
factors in here and I will show you in a
bit how this is just from a an an
overview of what kind of data you're
dealing with and what kind of data you
have in your application is very
effective but let's continue now with
the search to perform the similarity
search and actually see what this
difference in speed is so now let's run
this query again and so this is another
custom function to run the similarity
search on the new PG Vector object we
created and now let's run this and see
how long it takes this time all right so
we can see same result it retriev the
first chunk of the uh the book and you
can see that we're now at 0.29 seconds
so it's almost twice as fast and really
what I found is so there is some
variation every time you you run these
so let's see I can run run this one one
one more once more and see oh we're
0.23 now let's come back to the Pine con
one run this one one more time let's see
how long that takes and now we're at 0.5
seconds so really from these examples
that we have over here PG factor is
literally twice as fast and that's
really what I've seen uh consistently
been the case with the applications that
that I'm building right now and um that
really for me defeated the purpose of
using something dedicated like pine cone
and why this is the case is explained to
some degree in this document but it
basically highlights that since you
interact with all of these services
using apis not necessarily the
implementation and speed of the
algorithm and the search becomes the
bottleneck but the network connection
over which the data is sent so by using
an open- Source database like postrest
SQL you can put your database
essentially close to where your
application is running and this can
reduce latencies and now next where I
think PG Factor really shines is if we
start to add more data to it so let's
say we have another txt file let's load
that up split it up into chunks give it
a collection name two and let's run that
one more time let's see what happens
over here we can now come back to our
database we can refresh this and here we
have another collection that's in here
and now we can come over here refresh
refesh this notice we're now at 102 rows
and now we're at a lot more rows adding
more data to it this just to me gives me
a much better overview of what's
actually in my application and does also
my client's applications and if I
compare that to the few that I have over
here in the pine cone console I just
really prefer having an dedicated
application that I can use to go through
my data and also not only query on the
embeddings but also on the documents
query on the collection ideas and I just
feel more in control this way versus if
I come over here it starts with a random
factor that you get by default then it
shows you some results you can query by
ID but I don't store IDs otherwise you
would need a sep separate database which
kind of like defeats the purpose right
so that I think summarizes my issues
that I had with pine cone and now I am
aware it probably has to do something
with name spaces and configuring
everything using namespaces accordingly
to for example how I do this with uh
collections in here but again as I said
I just look at it from a speed
perspective and a Simplicity perspective
if I look at the examples over here PG
Factor wins in terms of speed it's open
source and I also just like being able
to open the database and see what's
going on and now one final thing that I
want to show you and this is really
powerful you can steal this from me I
built a custom PG Factor surface uh with
a custom similarity search with scores
that allows you to use Lang chain and
perform a similarity search over
multiple collections so out of the books
you can only uh perform a similarity
search on one collection but this uh
surfice will allow you to do so over all
of your data so we can look at this uh
service over here initialize it and then
we can run it and then run the query and
then it will use all of the data that's
in here now why is this useful that is
because right now what you can do is you
can very
easily add more data to Defector
database and be in full control so for
example let's see I can use that same
surface to delete collection one so
let's do that let's update this and here
it's instantly so here you can see I can
remove uh those I can remove those and
now that's gone and now I can come in
here delete collection 2 and again it
will be instant and it's gone in a
similar fashion I can just
reupload that data to the database let's
see so we have all of our documents in
here let's do it one more time and we
create the first collection again all
right so now we're back I can reload
this and here you can see now we have
all of that data again so it's a very
effective way to manage your data and
really what I found once you you get
through the POC with projects you're
working on it becomes much more about
upgrading and improving the data sets
than it is about proving the application
so what you will naturally see is in the
beginning the client or whatever you're
working on you will have a fixed set of
of documents of data that you want to
put in there you do some tests you
validate that this is this is a cool ID
and it works but that that is really
where the actual testing starts and
where continuous Improvement of the data
set comes into play this setup that you
have over here works very effective for
that and you can even build your own uis
guis around these delete collection and
update collection functions which is
what I've uh done using an aure storage
account with some web hooks to very
effectively manage everything that's
going on over here and just have one
simple query that searches through
everything so if you're working on large
language model applications right now
and you're using a dedic at Factor
database like pine cone or we8 I would
highly recommend looking into PG factor
and at least give it a shot see if it
works for you see if it makes sense for
you so how do you set up the postour SQL
database well what you can do is you can
have a look at either super base which I
really like um you can start for free
and what you will get is you will get a
managed postgress database and you can
enable the factor extension and that is
just for free so that's one option you
can also do it like I do it locally
right now or just put it on a server
wherever you want to deploy it or what I
do for most of my client Pro projects I
use a manage progress SQL database
through Microsoft Azure because that's
why I deploy my apps anyway so then it's
all hosted in there so those are just
some ideas for you to start
experimenting with it it's also worth
reading through this article which I
will link to you as well and that's
really what I wanted to show you in this
quick video it's something I've been
working on and I really use my YouTube
channel as a way to communicate what I
encounter in my work what I learn and
then give that back to you guys so if
that sounds interesting to you you want
to learn more about that make sure to
hit that subscribe button and if you're
interested in more AI lessons or lessons
that I learned working with these
generative AI projects then make sure to
check out this video next